<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A position maintained by I.B. before the late Earle of Huntingdon: viz. Priests are executed not for religion, but for treason</title>
            <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1334.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1226:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A position maintained by I.B. before the late Earle of Huntingdon: viz. Priests are executed not for religion, but for treason</title>
                  <author>Balmford, James, b. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Newly imprinted,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I. B. = James Balmford.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 1044.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1044 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cornell University. Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A POSITION MAINTAINED BY I.B. BEFORE THE LATE Earle of Huntingdon:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>viz. Prieſts are executed not for Religion, but for treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of a griffin with a winged orb suspended from a stone or book (McKerrow,
no. 246), copied from Sebastianus Gryphius, 1493-1556, and possibly passed to Richard Field in
1588-9</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Newly imprinted. 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17806:3"/>
            <head>A POSITION MAINTAINED BY I.B. BEFORE THE LATE EARLE OF HVNTINDON, viz. Prieſts are
executed, not <hi>for religion, but for treaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not to be denied, that Prieſts are executed for <hi>affirming the Popes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi>
and reconciling to the pretended Church of Rome, &amp;c. which are points of their ſuppoſed
religion: But yet they are not executed for theſe (or like) points or partes as they be
religious, but as they be trayterous, or dangerous to the ſtate, in ciuill conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For, if Prieſts were executed for theſe, or like points, as they be religious, then
the Church would proceed againſt them in Eccleſiaſticall maner, before the ſecular power
execute ciuill puniſhment.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17806:4"/>As againſt Anabaptiſtes, and other in this
Queenes raigne, hath bene performed. So that Prieſts their caſe differeth from Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets only
<hi>Secundum magis &amp; minus,</hi> the one being more dangerous in ciuill conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration then
the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, they ſhould be executed as wel for affirming the Popes primacy and
reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciling, &amp;c. (as Story for his miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, though) beyond ſeas. For ſuch
affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the primacie and reconciling, &amp;c. are as damnable in religious conſideration on
one ſide of the ſeas, as on the other, but not ſo dangerous to our ſtate in ciuill
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, they ſhould be executed as well for other points of popery: as giuing the
glory of the Creator (to wit prayer and praiſe) to creatures, Angels, Saints, ſtockes, and
ſtones, &amp;c. being no leſſe damnable then ſuch affirming the Popes primacy and
reconciling, &amp;c. in religious conſideration, but not ſo dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill
conſideration. As may appeare by a like caſe propounded.</p>
            <p>If Anabaptiſtes, denying <hi>magiſtracy,</hi> and <hi>that Chriſt tooke fleſh of the
Virgen Mary,</hi> ſhould ſwarme in England, and if
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17806:4"/>Magiſtrates ſhould puniſh in a more ciuill
manner of proceeding, not the latter (though no leſſe damnable, as it is religious) but the
former, being more dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who would ſay, that
Anabaptiſtes did ſuffer for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and not for treaſon or felony?</p>
            <p n="4">4 That affirming the Popes primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. may appeare directly to be
dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and therefore trayterous; it is to be knowne
and conſidered, that Pope Pius Quintus (by his bull declaratory) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced our gracious and
Chriſtian Queene <hi>an hereticke,</hi> and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all ſuch as yeeld obedience to her.
If then the Popes authority be perſwaded as as a matter of conſcience, &amp; if by
reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation her Maieſties ſubiects become vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed members of ſuch an head as is her
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall enemy, we may be aſſured that ſo many as are ſo perſwaded and reconciled, are
prepared to obey the Pope, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the Prince. Is not then ſuch affirming the Popes
primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. dangerous to the ſtate, in ciuill conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and
therefore trayterous?</p>
            <p n="5">5 In that I ſay (prepared) it is yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17806:5"/>to be knowne and conſidered: that whereas the
Earles had ill ſucceſſe in executing the ſaid bull, other deuiſes were fruſtrated, and
the hope of Papiſts their preſent preuailing much failed, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Campion (Engliſh
Prieſts) being to come into England to vrge the ſayd bull, and doubting that (in the rigour
thereof) it would not be readily obeyed, did craue and obtaine of Pope Gregory the thirteenth, this
expoſition more plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to Papiſts, but more dangerous to the ſtate: <hi>That the ſaid
bull may alway bind the Queene and heretickes: but Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> (that is Papiſts) <hi>in no
ſort, things ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they do, but then onely, when there may be publike execution
thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">Philopater a louer of his country (as he pretendeth by that fained name) no Engliſhman
(if ye will beleeue him) yet deſcended of the Engliſh nation (as he ſaith himſelfe) in a
poyſonfull and trayterous booke, often printed in diuerſe places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſeas (ſuch
liking find ſuch books with ſuch ſubiects as Papiſts be) graunteth that Prieſts are
ſent, with authority from the Pope,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> to pardon,
excommunicate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile, and teach (according to the bul ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17806:5"/>that ſubiects are not to obey the Queene in
ſpirituall matters, but in ciuill, and <hi>that for the preſent-ſtate of things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 What is implied in this laſt clauſe, Philopater himſelfe diſcouereth when he
ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> that it is agreed among diuerſe Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and
ſchoolemen, that if a Prince faile from the Romane faith, and endeuour to withdraw other,
ſubiects <hi>may and ought</hi> oppoſe themſelues, &amp; depoſe their Princes, <hi>if they
haue force.</hi> Which prouiſo, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcateth and vrgeth with this reaſon: <hi>Leaſt
religion ſhould be indammaged, and aduanced, attempts not preuailing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 The ſame Philopater doth perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily pronounce as tyrannicall, this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion moued
to Prieſts, fugitiues, recuſants, and ſuch like: <hi>If the Pope, or other in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe
and cauſe of religion, ſhould inuade the land, what part would you take, the Popes or the
Princes?</hi> His reaſon of miſlike is, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a rich Papiſt cannot anſwere freely
thereunto, without offence to God or Caeſar.</hi> As if God were offended, if Caeſar defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
againſt the Pope.</p>
            <p>By which expoſition of the bull, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Prieſts, and miſlike of a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
ſo neceſſary, it doth clearely appeare,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17806:6"/>that the end of affirming the Popes prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and
reconciling, &amp;c. is to prepare her Maieſties ſubiects to be ready (vpon paine of
excommunication) to ioyne with ſuch forces as ſhall be imploied againſt our Queene and
ſtate, in a pretended cauſe of religion. Is not this dangerous to the ſtate in ciuill
conſideration, and therefore tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous?</p>
            <p n="9">Let the affects and effects of ſuch teachers and ſchollers be obſerued, and the
truth of this aſſertion will be ſo euident, as that nothing can be more manifeſt. To let
paſſe their broad ſpeeches, when and where they dare: their concealing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betting
traytours, and trayterous deſignes, as they may (poſſibly) without danger, their reioycing
at, and ſpreading abroad newes, importing ſucceſſe to the Pope, though danger to the
Prince, &amp;c. To omit (I ſay) theſe and many ſuch arguments of their trayterous affection,
the ſhamefull practiſes of many, bewray the Popiſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of moſt, if opportunity
once ſerue. Many haue bene the conſpiracies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Maieſties perſon, to take away
her life. <hi>But ô Lord haue mercy vpon vs, to perſerue her.</hi> Many haue bene the
treaſons
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17806:6"/>againſt the land to deſtroy it. <hi>But
ô holy one of Iſrael defend this thine inheritance.</hi> Who haue bene the authors and
actors of all theſe tragicall attempts, but ſuch teachers and ſchollers? What were the rebels
in the North? And were they not prouoked to rebellion by Nicholas Morton Prieſt, ſent from Pope
Pius, to vrge the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his bull? What were the rebels in Ireland? And was not Nicholas
Sanders a Iudas (that is) a leader to the Popes army, that came in pretence to relieue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Parry
&amp; Sommeruile went about to murther her Maieſty. The one was encouraged in his diuelliſh
enterpriſe, by Cardinal Como, in the name of the Pope: and ſhall we thinke that the other
wanted the holy counſell of Hall the Prieſt arraigned? Babington and his complices, conſpired
againſt Prince and countrey. Was not Ballard Prieſt a chiefe counſellour to them? and did not
Boſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prieſt keepe counſell (at leaſt)
as he lately <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfeſſed? If then teachers and
ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Prieſts and Papiſts, concurre in ſeeking and following all oportunities to
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert our ſtate, can any other end be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined of Prieſts, their perſwading, and
reconciling, but to prepare their ſchollers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17806:7"/>to ioyne together againſt Prince and countrey,
when force ſhall anſwere their affection.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the multitude of reſolued Papiſts, be thus poyſoned and prepared, let this
be your laſt conſideration for this time, and not the leaſt at any time. That as the king of
Aſhur purpoſing to beſiege Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi>
32.9.12.13.</note> ſent from Laciſh Rabſhaketh and others, to weaken the hands of the people,
by diſgracing their king Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah, as one without religion, in that he had taken away altars,
and defaced high places; and by aduancing Saneherib, as one that preuailed againſt all gods. So
theſe locuſts, which haue faces of men, and haire of women,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi>
9.3.78.10.11.</note> but the ſtings of ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions in their tailes, to wit, Prieſts, who
pretend a tender care of ſauing ſoules in the beginning, but intend a cruell deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of
life and land in the end, are ſent into this realme by their king (the Angell of the
bottomleſſe pit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7.4.</note> out of the ſmoke thereof,
namely, by the Pope in his fume, but without flame I truſt) before inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on intended, to
weaken the hands, and withdraw the harts of the people, from our gracious Queene, by diſgracing
her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17806:7"/>as one without religion, in that ſhe hath taken
away ſacrificing altars, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced religious houſes; and by aduancing their king, as one
that preuaileth againſt all gods, all ſtates, all religions. The like practiſe of ſending
Prieſts to prepare peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt the comming in of Spaniards, is to be perceiued in
Scotland.</p>
            <p n="11">11 What ſucceſſe this deuiſe hath, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be conſidered. The Pope is
certified by Cardinall Allen, and the king of Spaine by Parſons the Prieſts, that there ſhall
be found (ready ſecretly within her Maieſties dominions) many thouſands of able peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that
will be ready to aſſiſt ſuch power as ſhall be ſet on land. Of whoſe names they haue
deliuered bead-roles, eſpecially of ſuch as dwell in port Townes, and on the ſea coaſt,
with aſſurance that Prieſts ſhall continue their reconciled people, in their lewd
conſtancy. So hath her Maieſty publiſhed in her Declaration, Anno 1591. But Philopater
denieth it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> How impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and barely without any
reaſon. But if Ballard Prieſt ſent ſuch a bead-role into Spaine, and Throgmorton had
gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the names of popiſh Noblemen and Gentlemen, to the ſame purpoſe: It may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17806:8"/>be (in reaſon) ſuppoſed, that to Prieſts
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence is ſent by Prieſts, what ſchollers they haue perſwaded and prepared for
treaſon and rebellion.</p>
            <p>To conclude, 1. If the Church proceed not againſt Prieſts in Eccleſiaſticall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
before the ſecular power execute them. 2. If Prieſts ſuffer not for affirming the Popes
primacy and reconciling, &amp;c. beyond ſeas. 3. If Prieſts be not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for other points
of popery, no leſſe damnable then theſe, as they be religious. 4. But if the Pope by his
bull, hath vpon paine of excommunication diſcharged her Maieſties ſubiects of their
allegiance. 5. If Papiſts be diſpenſed with, for obeying her Maieſty til time ſerue to
the contrary. 6. If Prieſts come of purpoſe to reconcile and teach according to the bull
expounded. 7. If it be a catholike doctrine, that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects hauing force, ought to depoſe their
Prince, maintaining religion contrary to the Church of Rome: &amp; 8. In that caſe to ioyne with
forreigne power. 9. If maiſters and ſchollers haue from time to time at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to put the
ſayd bull in execution. 10. If Prieſts be ſent before inuaſion to prepare the people: and
11. If thouſands
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17806:8"/>be notified euen by Prieſts prepared: then it
may be auouched, that Prieſts are not executed for affirming the Popes primacy and reconciling,
&amp;c. as they be religious, but as they be trayterous, or dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the ſtate in ciuill
conſideration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17806:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
